<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Altare evangelicum. A sermon preached at Christ-Church in Dublin, on the 27th of April Before his Excellency Arthur Earl of Essex, Lord Lieutenant General, and general governour of the kingdom of Ireland. By Edward Lord Bishop of Clonsert and Kilmac-Duah. Published by his Excellencies order and command.</title>
            <author>Wolley, Edward, 1603-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828877</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1962:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Altare evangelicum. A sermon preached at Christ-Church in Dublin, on the 27th of April Before his Excellency Arthur Earl of Essex, Lord Lieutenant General, and general governour of the kingdom of Ireland. By Edward Lord Bishop of Clonsert and Kilmac-Duah. Published by his Excellencies order and command.</title>
                  <author>Wolley, Edward, 1603-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Benjamin Tooke, printer to the King's most Excellent Majesty; and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde, book-seller in Castle-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Edvardus Clonsertensis, i.e. Edward Wolley.</note>
                  <note>Heading on p. 1 reads: Gen. 35. 7. And he built there an altar, and called the place El-Bethel, because there God appeared unto him, when he fled from the face of his brother.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33310:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33310:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Altare Evangelicum.</hi> A SERMON Preached at Chriſt-Church IN DUBLIN, On the 27th of <hi>April.</hi> Before his <hi>Excellency</hi> ARTHUR Earl of ESSEX, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of the Kingdom of IRELAND. <hi>By</hi> EDWARD <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Clonfert <hi> and</hi> Kilmac-Duah.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Publiſhed by his Excellencies Order and Command.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the KING's moſt Excellent Majeſty; And are to be Sold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde,</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33310:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33310:2"/>
            <head>To his Excellency ARTHUR EARL of ESSEX, Viſcount <hi>Malden,</hi> Baron CAPEL of <hi>Hadbam,</hi> Lord Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and General Governour of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> and one of the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Council.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a high Degree of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> truſt and confidence in your <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33310:3"/>great abilities, to ſettle and eſtabliſh You his <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> Chief Governour in this his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſo it is received as an act of Grace and Kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all loyal and good ſubjects in this Land, to be under the Umbrage and Protection of your Virtues and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which ſince your Excellencies Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, have much refreſhed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted many drooping hearts, and raiſed them to future hopeful expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and as to diſcontents (if any) ſuch is your Piety, Wiſedom, and Juſtice, that they all are calmed and allayed, or ſo quieted, that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not at all. And it is a happy Juncture, when the Church, the
<pb facs="tcp:33310:3"/>State, the Army, make no complaints or clamours, but, as the members of the Body to the Head, yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Chief Governour. As this may be the ground and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the univerſal Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of this Kingdom at preſent, and great ſatisfaction to all, though of different perſwaſion; ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it will improve and unite all His MAJESTIES Subjects to more perfect and exact obedience, which hath likewiſe bound me to obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and (on this accompt) to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and make legible, what was for a ſhort time onely in your Excellencies, and the Chriſtian Auditors ears. And no cenſure is to be feared, where
<pb facs="tcp:33310:4"/>your <hi>Excellency</hi> will pleaſe to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or Patronize,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Excellencies Devoted And moſt humble Servant</hi> Edvardus Clonfertenſis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33310:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>GEN. 35.7.</hi> And he built there an Altar, and called the place <hi>El-Bethel,</hi> becauſe there God appeared unto him, when he fled from the face of his Brother.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Text, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſets forth the Pious example of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> Erecting and Building an Altar to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, for his deliverance from the rage and fury of his bloudy Brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> In which words <hi>Moſes</hi> records, Firſt, that the Patriarch performed his duty: for <hi>aedificavit Altare,</hi> he built an Altar,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Duty</hi>
               </note> Secondly,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33310:5"/>That God ſent the Patriarch his deliverance,<note place="margin">Officium Jacobi. 2. <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> Auxilium Dei. 3. <hi>Danger.</hi> Odium <hi>Eſaui.</hi> Exercitium. Actus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votionis. vel Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum. 2. Opus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicationis.</note> implyed in theſe words, <hi>That God appeared unto him.</hi> Thirdly, his danger is diſcovered in the laſt words. <hi>Moſes</hi> teſtifieth that he was forced to fly from the face and fury of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> or elſe, if you pleaſe, ſee another Diviſion and Paraphraſe on the Text. Firſt, here is <hi>Actus Devotionis,</hi> an Act of High and holy Devotion, a bleſſed example of Piety, and a great Teſtimony of thankfulneſs to Almighty God for won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and great deliverance. <hi>Aedificavit Altare,</hi> and he built an Altar there. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, here is <hi>Opus Dedicationis,</hi> the Noble work of Dedication of an Altar Erected and Built. <hi>Jacob</hi> deſigns chiefly Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in this work, and dedicateth his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar to his Deliverer, giving God the glory of his ſafety, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocavit locum El-Bethel,</hi> that is the God of <hi>Bethel,</hi> or rather the God of Gods houſe before called <hi>Luz,</hi> but now <hi>Bethel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, here is <hi>Argumentum Reſolutionis,</hi> the Reaſon,<note place="margin">3. Elenchus vel Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Reſo-</note> ground, and cauſe, of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs Pious and holy Reſolutions. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33310:5"/>ſaith Moſes, <hi>quia apparuit Deus,</hi> God appeared to him when he fled from the face of his Brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> Of theſe in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And firſt of the Patriarchs Acts of Piety and Devotion in theſe words, <hi>Aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavit Altare.</hi> In the Frontiſpiece of the Text you may ſee Firſt <hi>Opificem:</hi> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, the founder or builder, of this piece of Devotion ſet forth in the Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>Ille,</hi> he:<note place="margin">1. Opifiex Gen. 35.6. Gen. 35.6. 2. Opus, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare.</note> that is (as in the verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Text) <hi>Jacob</hi> came to <hi>Luz,</hi> which is in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that is <hi>Bethel.</hi> Secondly, <hi>opus ipſum</hi> the work it ſelf. And that is <hi>Altare:</hi> an Altar or a holy place, to Sacrifice to Almighty God; which was the moſt Ancient, Innocent, Primitive,<note place="margin">3. Locusvel ſedes ſituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, <hi>Ibi. there</hi>
               </note> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſerving of God. Thirdly, here is <hi>locus</hi> or <hi>ſedes Altaris,</hi> the place or Scituation where this Altar was ſeated; <hi>Ibi,</hi> in this Adverb of place, that is in the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> and more particularly in the place called <hi>Bethel.</hi> I have now opened the Text: I ſhall begin with the great exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar of Piety, That is <hi>Jacob:</hi> A perſon of whom I find, the holy Scripture make as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33310:6"/>honourable and eminent mention, as of any of all the holy Patriarchs St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> meditating on this ſubject,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Divus Bernard. <hi>in Sententijs</hi> Quater lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatus eſt <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> in utero cum <hi>Eſauo,</hi> in Adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia cum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem; in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotamia cum Laban, in <hi>Bethel</hi> cum <hi>Angelo.</hi>
               </note> ſaith, That the Patriarch <hi>Jacob</hi> was for many tryals and temptations, which did ſet forth his Faith, Hope, Charity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Patience, Obedience, and all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Virtues and Graces that might beautifie his bleſſed ſoul. But St. <hi>Bernard</hi> chiefly reduceth them to four more remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Paſſages and Re-encounters which the Patriarch ſuffered,<note n="1" place="margin">Lucta in utero matris.</note> and ſucceeded with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory out of them all. The Firſt was, <hi>Lucta in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tero Matris,</hi> a fight or ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his Mother <hi>Rebecca</hi>'s womb with his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> which cauſed <hi>Rebecca</hi> to complain,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 25 22.23. <hi>Collide ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in utero Parvuli.</hi> Common Tranſla.</note> ſaying, <hi>The children ſtruggle with me;</hi> and ſhe ſaid, <hi>Why am I thus?</hi> And ſhe went to enquire of the Lord, and the Lord ſaid unto her, <hi>Two Nations are in thy womb, and two manner of People ſhall be ſeparated from thy bowels; and the one People ſhall be ſtronger than the other People, and the elder ſhall ſerve the younger.</hi> A ſtrange Paſſage, that Twins could not be quiet <hi>in domo Naturae,</hi> in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33310:6"/>firſt Houſe; but, being little more than Embryo's, did claſh and fight in their Mothers womb. This was certainly <hi>Pugna Prophetica,</hi> an early fight,<note place="margin">Pugna Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetica.</note> that prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied and foretold the world, That the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> might have <hi>Jacobs</hi> and <hi>Eſaus,</hi> good men and bad in her womb, <hi>Eſauites</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> prophane perſons and pious Votaries; proud <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> and penitent <hi>Publicans,</hi> ſuperſtitious <hi>Papists,</hi> and ſeditious <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> as well as Orthodox <hi>Chriſtians</hi> at the ſame time in the Temple. Secondly,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da lucta in <hi>Domo Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris.</hi>
               </note> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Jacob</hi> had <hi>luctam in domo Patris,</hi> a ſad trouble and daily grievous vexation in his Fathers houſe, where <hi>Eſau</hi> his Elder Brother expreſſed nothing, but miſchief and malice, wrath and fury, death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards his younger Brother <hi>Jacob,</hi> whom <hi>Eſau</hi> firſt aſperſed with contumely and dirty language,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 27.36. Gen. 27.41.</note> calling him a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planter, and then having wounded his name with a venemous tongue, deſigned his death with a malicious heart and hand againſt whoſe unnatural rage and wrath <hi>Obadiah</hi> compoſed chiefly his Prophecy;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33310:7"/>ſaying,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah, v. 10.</note> 
               <hi>For thy violence againſt thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for ever.</hi> Thus by Gods bleſſing, and <hi>Rebeccahs</hi> Council, <hi>Jacob</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped his Brothers fury, and preſerved himſelf alive.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen. 27.43.</note> It ſeemeth by <hi>Eſau</hi>'s malicious practice (being not onely <hi>frater,</hi> a Brother, but <hi>Bimulus</hi> a Twin, of the ſame Conception and Generation) no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation though never ſo near; can protect an innocent plain perſon, from the rancor and malice of a malicious, envious, wicked heart. This was <hi>Jacobs</hi> unhappy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his unnatural out-ragious Brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> The third Tryal and trouble that this Patriark had was<note n="(h)" place="margin">Tertia lucta in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Servitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in Domo Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trui Laban,</hi> in his Uncle <hi>Labans</hi> houſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he fled for refuge and Protection from his Brother; fury and malice. But his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment there proved (as it appears) rather ſlavery then ſecurity, rather inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable dureſs and hardſhip, than the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of a Kinſman. Hear <hi>Jacob</hi> s own words in his ſad complaints<note n="(i)" place="margin">Gen. 31.38, 39, 41, 42.</note> ſaying, <hi>I what is my Treſpaſs, what is my Sin,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33310:7"/>that thou ſo hotly purſueſt after me,</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> (as if a Cheat, a Theif, a Robber), <hi>I have been Twenty years in thy houſe, and thou changeſt my wages Ten times. The Drought conſumed me in the day, and the Froſt by night; God hath ſeen my Affliction and the labour of my hands.</hi> Thus was <hi>Jacob</hi> uſed by his Uncle <hi>Laban;</hi> But God delivered him out of his hands, and reſcued his Innocency from <hi>Labans</hi> unmerciful uſage: This was a third extremity and ſlavery, that <hi>Jacob</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from by the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the fear of <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Father.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Gen. 31.42.</note> Hence obſerve, that kindred and Relations, are but tickle Tenures, and uncertain Comforts, unleſs Grace and vertue, Piety and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sanctifie and govern the Affections and hearts of the neareſt Relations. And now hear a word of <hi>Jacobs</hi> fourth Conteſt and Agony, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>non ſolum cum fratre:</hi> not onely, with his Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> or Uncle <hi>Laban,</hi> but (which was a higher tryal than the other three) <hi>Luctatus cum Angelo in</hi> Bethel.<note n="(m)" place="margin">4. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta cum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo in <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Moſes</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords the ſtory: <hi>And</hi> Jacob <hi>was left alone,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33310:8"/>and there wreſtled a man</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Gen. 32.24.</note> 
               <hi>with him untill the break of the day,</hi> which happy meeting in the Field, was ordained by God himſelf, who ſent<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, forma hominis.</note> his Angels firſt as Harbingers to meet <hi>Jacob,</hi> as his Comforters and Conductors: and when <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw them, he ſaid, <hi>This is Gods hoſt</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Gen. 32.1.</note> 
               <hi>and he called the name of that place</hi> Mahanaim. Thus God protecteth his ſervants by <hi>miniſtring ſpirits</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Maha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naim. i. e.</hi> Two hoſts. Heb. 1.14.</note> as he promiſeth; <hi>They ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to keep thee in all thy wayes.</hi> But this is not all, God hath more honour, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and comfort, for <hi>Jacob,</hi> than the preſence or company of Angels. For the Patriarch returning by God's command in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal. 91.11.</note> own Countrey, after Twenty years exile, ſervitude, and ſlavery, and being to re-encounter with the rage and fury of a malicious enemy, his unnatural brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> who was advancing with a party of Four hundred men, reſolved to kill and deſtroy the Patriarch with his Wives and Children, with all his innocent and unarmed Company;<note n="(s)" place="margin">Gen. 31.3, 13.</note> In this diſtreſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33310:8"/>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> was greatly affraid,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Gen. 32.11.</note> his fears encreaſed, and his heart did tremble. In this his ſadneſs of his ſoul, he hath no hopes but in God, no means but Prayer, no ſhield but Faith. And therefore in this great Tryal, he maketh his Addreſſes to the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſaying,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Gen. 32.7.</note> 
               <hi>Deliver me O God, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of</hi> Eſau, <hi>for I fear him, leſt he will come and ſmite me, with the mother and the children.</hi> In his Prayer, he likewiſe remembreth God of his grace and promiſe;<note n="(x)" place="margin">Gen. 32.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſayeſt, I will ſurely do thee good, and make thy ſeed as the ſand of the ſea, which cannot be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred for multitude.</hi> God heard his Prayer, and made good his promiſe, by appeaſing <hi>Eſau</hi>'s fury, and preſerving his ſervant <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> and to aſcertain and evidence his Truth, God is pleaſed to wreſtle with him, to try his ſervant <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſtrength by Faith, to keep company all night with his devotion, to yield a Victory, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Benediction, and to crown <hi>Jacob's</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33310:9"/>Conqueſt with a Title of Honour to all Ages:<note n="(y)" place="margin">Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi> eligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Noe,</hi> vocatur <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur <hi>Iſaac, Jacob</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um facie ad faciem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatur, D. <hi>Bern.</hi> ſerm. de ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, <hi>Joh. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſtâ</hi> pag. <hi>1683.</hi>
               </note> God himſelf, as the Fountain of all Honour, ſaying,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Gen. 32.28.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Name ſhall be no more called</hi> Jacob, <hi>but</hi> Iſrael; <hi>for as a Prince haſt thou power with God, and with men,</hi> and haſt prevailed. Thus was <hi>Jacob</hi> tryed, thus was <hi>Jacob</hi> honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, preſerved, and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 2.20.</note> bleſſed. This was the Fourth, and moſt ſolemn Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone and taſte of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s patience and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; his faith and devotion, his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and honour; by which Meditation ſee and know, that dangers and diſtreſſes are the Tryals of Faith in Gods ſervants. Fear and troubles make good men fly to their Prayers, and Prayers and fervent Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion prevail with God for preſervation and deliverances. I have now done with <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>'s Four ſeveral Tryals or Wreſtlings, and ſo quit any further Diſcourſe of <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Opifex, Fundator</hi> Jacob. 2. Part. <hi>Opus.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Founder</hi> or <hi>Builder,</hi> in the Text, and ſo ſhall lead you to take a View of <hi>Opus,</hi> or <hi>Aedificium,</hi> his ſacred <hi>Work</hi> or <hi>Edifice, He built an Altar.</hi> As afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſtreſs cauſed <hi>Jacob</hi> to fly to his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33310:9"/>Prayers, and Prayers and Devotion procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red deliverance from God: ſo in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and thankfulneſs, deliverance from danger, accompanied with advancement to Honours, work on the Patriarchs noble mind, to be viſibly devout, and to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence his Faith by good works. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch is not onely content to make Vowes,<note place="margin">Altare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numentum gratitudinis.</note> but he falls a building a pious pillar, <hi>in monumentum gratitudinis,</hi> as a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Monument of his devotion and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. <hi>Struxit Altare,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Struxit Altare.</note> He built an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, which was the firſt way and mode of Gods viſible Worſhip on earth ſince the world was created. Thus was <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Rabbi Solomon.</note> as the Jewes and Rabbins taught) direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Quire of Angels to ſerve God in Paradiſe: And thus <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. <hi>de</hi> l Cain <hi>&amp;</hi> Abe</note> as the Fathers ſay, inſtructed and enjoyned his two ſons, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> to bring their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and to worſhip at the Altar.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 4 3, 4.</note> According to this example, <hi>Noah</hi> built an altar, and offered Burnt-offerings on the altar; <hi>and the Lord ſmelled a ſweet ſavour from thoſe oblations.</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Gen. 8.20, 21.</note> Thus <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33310:10"/>built an Altar at <hi>Sichem,</hi> in the Plain of <hi>Moreh</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen. 12.7.</note> when in his Travels, and in a ſtrange Countrey, he was delivered from the <hi>Canaanite.</hi> Thus <hi>Iſaac</hi> built an Altar in <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> when he was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <hi>Philistines,</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Gen. 26.17, 25.</note> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious ſpirits of <hi>Gerar,</hi> And thus <hi>Jacob,</hi> that he might make out <hi>Patrium coluiſſe Deum,</hi> that he did worſhip the God of his Fathers, and in imitation of theſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Preſidents, <hi>ſtruxit Altare,</hi> he built an Altar, where he might worſhip God, and offer up holy Oblations; which piece of ſtructure you may the better judge of, if you pleaſe to take a view of it in its mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">1. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. 2. for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. 3. u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, finis. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</note>, form, or figure; or elſe in its uſe and end. Firſt for the matter, <hi>ex quâ,</hi> of which the Altar may be compos'd or made; I find it various and indifferent, whether made of earth, of ſtone, of wood, of braſs, or gold: The Scripture menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons all theſe kinds, leſt there ſhould be exception at any, God looking more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly at the affections and heart of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Founder and Benefactor, than at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33310:10"/>the work, though never ſo ſtately or coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thus God commanded <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Exod. 20.24. 1. Altare Terreum. rum.</note> ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt make me an Altar of earth, and ſacrifice thy Burnt-offerings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> In the ſervice of the Tabernacle, God will have <hi>Moſes</hi> to make an Altar<note n="(k)" place="margin">Exod. 27.1. 2. Altare ligneum. 3. Altare lapideum.</note> of <hi>Shittim</hi> wood, more proper and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for that moving and travelling Tent or Tabernacle. <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who was <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps militiae,</hi> chief Captain and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der over all the Forces in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Moſes,</hi> in thankfulneſs for his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Victories, built an altar of ſtone,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Joſua 8.30.</note> and there they offered their Burnt-offerings to the Lord. When the Church was advanced from a Tabernacle to a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in King <hi>Solomon</hi>'s happy Reign, that Princely Monarch made a ſtately Altar of Braſs,<note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Chro. 41. 1 4. Altare Aeneum.</note> Twenty cubits in length, and Twenty cubits in breadth, a Royal Piece, ſuitable to the State of that magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Temple.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, We read that this noble King in his pious affections, to Gods houſe framed an Altar of pure Gold <hi>(n)</hi> to Offer ſweet Incenſe,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33310:11"/>and perfumed odors, up to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty who had advanced him to His Royal Throne and Dignity<note n="(o)" place="margin">Materia Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>qua.</note> Thus as to the matter, whether the Altars were made of Earth, of Wood, of Stone, of braſs, or Gold it was Indifferent and various.<note n="(p)" place="margin">Forma &amp; figura Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taris.</note> Secondly, as to due form or figures ſome were of greater magnitude ſome of leſs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions;<note n="(q)" place="margin">Exod. 27.1. 2. Chro. 4.1. 1. King: 7.48.</note> Some of five, ſome of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Cubits; Some of one Cubit only: Some larger, Some leſſer, as God Commanded and Directed. And as God was pleaſed to give Rules in <hi>General</hi> for <hi>Moſes Tabernacle,</hi> and <hi>Solomons Temples,</hi> ſo in <hi>Particular,</hi> God ordered in what form and figure thoſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars ſhould be framed, that his ſervice might be the more exactly performed, and, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note n="(r)" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> In Gods Church <hi>all things might <hi>be done decently and in Order.</hi> But there is leſs Concern in the notion of the matter or form of Altars, But the uſe and end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is more Conſiderable<note n="(s)" place="margin">Vſus et Finis Altaris</note> And this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation chiefly wrought in the Patriarchs Soul, who being raiſed from a Low Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to a Noble quality, Delivered from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33310:11"/>ſervitude, reſcued from his Brothers fury, and ſo many dangers, and being advanced from being a Mean poor Shephard or ſervant to the eminent dignity of a Patriarch or Prince; he builds an <hi>Altar, ut Deum coleret,</hi> that he might adore and worſhip that Great and good God who had owned him with ſo many Signal Favours. The uſe then of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an<note n="(t)" place="margin">Th. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. 1.2. Quaes. 102.</note> 
                  <hi>Altar</hi> is for Gods worſhip and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Now to know how that may be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed, the School-men tell us that as in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceremonies of the Temple or the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſo in the building of an Altar, there is <hi>ratio</hi> or <hi>Status Literalis</hi> and <hi>Figuralis:</hi> A <hi>literal</hi> and <hi>figurall</hi> ſenſe or meaning. The <hi>literal</hi> ſenſe of the Altar was the viſible work,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Significat Chriſtum. 1.2. Quaes. 102. Altare ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Chriſti 3 q. 83.1.2. Heb. 9.28. Heb. 10.10.</note> the <hi>figural</hi> or <hi>myſtical</hi> was typified or ſignified by it. In the literal ſenſe the Altar was the Place where the ſacrifice was burnt and the Incense offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In the figural or myſtical ſenſe, the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> the Incenſe, the ſacrifice, did foretel Chriſt on the Croſs who was a Sacrifice, died for our Sins, and did offer us the Incenſe of his Devotion for the ſalvation of our ſouls. Give me leave to uſe another diſtinction to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33310:12"/>the uſe of <hi>Altars;</hi> which were either <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> and <hi>Patriarchal</hi> before the Law,<note place="margin">Altare. 1. Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chale. 2. Legale. 3. Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> or <hi>Legal</hi> and <hi>Levitical</hi> under the law, or elſe <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> and <hi>Evangelical</hi> under the Goſpell. By the firſt the Patriarchs, by the ſecond the <hi>Jewes</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by the third the Chriſtians were taught to adore and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God. This Altar in the Text was of the firſt kind,<note place="margin">Altare In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſi. Altare Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miamatis. Exod. 30.10. Revel. 8.3, 4, 5. Revel. 7.14. Sacrificia laudis, fidei, confeſſionis,</note> wherein <hi>Jacob,</hi> to evidence his Devotion, his thankfulneſs, his zeal, his piety, builds his Altar, to adore and worſhip God. And as the Patriarchs and Jewes had their <hi>Altaria, holocauſta, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationes:</hi> Altars, burnt-offerings, and obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſo the Chriſtians have their <hi>Altars</hi> or holy Tables, and their <hi>Sacrificia Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualia (nempe, laudis, fidei, confeſſionis, charitatis:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">charitatis: <hi>Auguſt. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorat.</hi> de ſcriptura. Situs Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae verſùs Orientem.</note>) Spiritual Sacrifices are offered wherewith Chriſtians adore and worſhip God. And as Piety and Devotion firſt built Churches; ſo a Religious and holy Prudence gave thoſe Church their figure, their forms, and ſcituations, directing thoſe ſacred buildings to be Eaſt and Weſt, their Iſles or Doors to be North and South
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33310:12"/>
                  <hi>(in formam &amp; memoriam Domini, extenſis brachijs, in crucem fixi)</hi> in ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance preſenting our bleſſed Saviour nailed on the Croſs, and theſe Churches the Primitive Fathers took care ſhould be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Fonts for Baptiſm; with Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits for Inſtruction; with Altars or Holy Tables for the Bleſſed Euchariſt and Holy Devotion.<note place="margin">1. Baptiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</note> The <hi>Baptiſterium</hi> or Front was ſcited at the Weſt end or Entrance of the Church, where the Chriſtians were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and matriculated into Chriſtianity. The <hi>Suggeſtum</hi> or Pulpit,<note place="margin">2. Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum.</note> was <hi>in medio Eccleſiae,</hi> where the Chriſtians might be better inſtructed with God's Will and Word. The <hi>Altar</hi> or Holy Table,<note place="margin">3. Altare.</note> was ſeated in the Eaſt End of the Church, for more eminent ſervice in God's Worſhip. Here the Church our Mother, teacheth the Clergy to read God's Commandments,<note place="margin">1. Decem Praecepta.</note> as <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons at the Altar or Holy Table, to inſtruct the People in their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Duty towards God, and towards man. Here the Prieſt is obliged to read the glad tidings of ſalvation choice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33310:13"/>wrapt up in the Epiſtles and Goſpels of the Day.<note place="margin">2. Epiſtola &amp; Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> Here is ſaid or ſung the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed,<note place="margin">3. Nicenum Symbolum, Anno ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis 320. Magdebur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſ. <hi>Cent.</hi> 4â folio 617. Rubrick. The Prayer of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. Lit. General Confeſſion.</note> compoſed by the Three hundred and eighteen Biſhops in that Council, called by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, to vindicate the Truth of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Eternal Godhead, and to ſuppreſs the venome and poyſon of the <hi>Arian</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Upon the Altar or holy Table the Church commands the conſecration of the Hoaſt and Bleſſed Euchariſt; Here the Prieſt and People make general Confeſſion of their ſins; Here the Biſhop, or Prieſt, pronounceth the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſins; Here the worthy Receivers take and participate, by a lively Faith,<note place="margin">Church Catechiſm.</note> the real Preſence of the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Bleſſed Sacrament, to their eternal comfort; Here the Saints chant and ſing the Angels Song, ſaying, <hi>Gloria in excelſis, Glory be to God on high, on earth peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>good will towards men;</hi> and hence in the Cloſe, the Biſhop and Prieſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſeth the Holy Communicants with the Bleſſing of the Peace of God.<note place="margin">Rubrick for the Bleſſing.</note> Thus the Church our Mother ſets forth the uſe of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33310:13"/>The Altar or Holy Table. And beſides this Practice of Piety and Devotion, it is moſt obſervable that Chriſtian Emperors, Kings, and Sovereign Princes receive their<note n="(s)" place="margin">Regalia ab Altari.</note> 
                  <hi>Regalia,</hi> their Royal Diadems, their Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crowns, their Swords, their Scepters, from Gods Altars. Here they are anointed with Holy Oyle, and inveſted with Royal Robes. Here they receive the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as a pledge of their Piety, and take Sacred Oaths to defend Gods Church, and their Subjects, according to Law and Juſtice.<note place="margin">Spiritualia Cleri ab Altari.</note> And as Sovereign Chriſtians Princes are thus honoured, and thus honour Gods Altars; ſo Chriſtian Praelates, Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, here receive the Impoſition of Hands at their <hi>Conſecration</hi> and <hi>Ordination,</hi> when they make thoſe Sacred Proteſtations and Promiſes before Gods Altar to perform the Duties of their High and Holy Calling. And as Kings, and Prieſts, ſo the choiceſt of the Peers and Nobles in the famous order of the <hi>Knights of the Garter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſignia E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitum Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorum ab Altari.</note> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the honour of their inſtallation from Gods Altar; whence they receive their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignia,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33310:14"/>thoſe <hi>Royal marks</hi> of their Princes Truſt and Favour,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Edvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus III. ut milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem virtatem honoribus decorar et no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliſſimam conſcripſit Equitum Auratorum Societatem. <hi>Camden. Britanniâ.</hi>
                  </note> and the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evidences of their own worth, fidelity, and merits. Here the married couple make their vows to keep that holy ſtate and the bed undefiled, and hence they have the bleſſing; and Laſtly the holy Altar is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with the book of God (as the Ark that kept the Oracles)<note n="(u)" place="margin">Rom. 9.4. Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſuper <hi>Evangelium</hi> Opus Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> The <hi>bleſſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangels,</hi> on which Sacred piece the People are admitted to lay their hands, to kiſs with their mouths, as a Sacred obligation to utter truth, and to decide all differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Diſpute or Controverſie. Thus the Church our Mother, and Religion her Daughter, hath taught us the uſe of an Evangelical Altar. I have done with <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> building an Altar; and come to ſpeak of <hi>Locus,</hi> the place, where the Patriarch made choice to build, <hi>Ibi,</hi> There, that is at <hi>Bethel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Parte <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi> Bethel.</note> Now <hi>Bethel</hi> was a City of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Joſua. 18.13.</note> on the Southward betwixt <hi>Jordan</hi> and <hi>Jericho,</hi> antiently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Luz;</hi> here <hi>Jacob</hi> in his Travels, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſave his life was benighted, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33310:14"/>lighted <hi>on a certain place, and tarried there all night.</hi>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">Gen. 28.11, 12. cuſtodes <hi>Angeli.</hi> conſolator <hi>Deus.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He took the ſtones of the place, and put them for his pillows, and lay down in the place to ſleep, and he dreamed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a ladder ſet on the earth, and the top of it reached Heaven, and behold the Angel of God aſcending and deſcending on it: And behold the Lord ſtood about it and ſaid, I am the Lord God of thy Father</hi> Abraham, <hi>and the God of</hi> Iſaac: <hi>The land whereon thou lyeſt to thee will I give it and to thy ſeed. And in thy ſeed</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">Gen. 12.3, 18, 18, 22, 18, 26, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall all the Nations of the Earth be bleſſed.</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 28.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold I am with thee, and will keep thee in all places whither thou goeſt.</hi> Theſe were ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn promiſes of grace and favour, as the like were never to be Parallel'd. And as God was infinitely <hi>gracious</hi> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſo the Patriarch to his power will be <hi>dutiful, grateful</hi> and <hi>obſequious.</hi> For as ſoon as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> awaketh out of ſleep<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen.</note> he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his faith, his hope, his charity: his <hi>faith</hi> ſaying, <hi>ſurely the Lord is in this place, and I knew it not.</hi> Secondly his <hi>hope,</hi> both admiring and adoring, when he ſaid,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33310:15"/>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 28.17. Domus Dei <hi>Porta Caeli.</hi>
                  </note> This is none other but the Houſe of God, and gate of Heaven.</hi> Thirdly his <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> love and zeal to Gods honour:<note n="(d)" place="margin">Gen. 28.18, 19.</note> for he <hi>roſe up early in the morning, and took the ſtone that he had put for his pillow, and ſet it up for a pillar, and poured oyl on the top of it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>i.e.</hi> Domus Dei.</note> 
               <hi>and he called the name of that place</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen, 28.19.</note> Bethel when <hi>Jacob</hi> had erected his pillar he made his vow, ſaying, <hi>If God will be with me and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat and raiment to put on, ſo that I come again to my Fathers houſe in peace; then ſhall the Lord be my God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.20.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>and this ſtone which I have ſet for a pillar ſhall be Gods houſe, and of all that thou ſhalt give me, ſurely I will give the tenth unto thee.</hi> Thus you have ſeen the Patriarch's Devotion, and heard his own reaſons why he made choice to build his Altar at <hi>Bethel:</hi> yet here further it was not onely a place of <hi>Jacobs</hi> choice, but likewiſe the Altar was built there by Gods Command. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> records the ſacred ſtory: God ſaid unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> ariſe, go up to <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 35.1.</note> and dwell there, and make there an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33310:15"/>Altar unto God, that appeared unto thee when thou fleddeſt from the face of <hi>Eſau</hi> thy Brother. It is then likely to be a good work, a bleſſed piece, when Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and Mans affection agree in Gods worſhip and ſervice, when God directeth, and Man obeyeth in the building of an <hi>Altar,</hi> a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> a <hi>Table,</hi> a <hi>Church,</hi> a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue.</hi> And <hi>except the Lord bleſs the</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 127.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>houſe, the builders build in vain.</hi> Such a houſe may prove not the <hi>houſe of God,</hi> but a <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> not a <hi>Bethel,</hi> but a <hi>Bethaven.</hi> See then the ſafeſt way for ſacred ſtructures, is,<note place="margin">Domus Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis.</note> when God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and man then obeyeth; And yet ſee the Patriarchs Wiſdom, and Pious pauſe; he will not build an Altar at <hi>Bethel,</hi> but with Counſel &amp; conſultations. Holy Buildings, and ſacred things, are not to be attempted by raſh heads, or rude hands.<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.6.</note> This was King <hi>David</hi>'s courſe, ſaying, <hi>I will waſh my hands in innocency, ſo will I go to thine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, O Lord, as not fit for holy approaches, with either hollow hearts, or polluted hands.</hi> And as innocency was the Patriarch's Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33310:16"/>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122. 1.</note> ſo holy Society was his comfort; and therefore King <hi>David,</hi> ſeemeth to rejoyce at the very hopes of building an Altar for Gods Service; and the good man will have his whole Houſhold ſhare with him in the Bleſsing of his Devotion. And therefore <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaith unto his Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.2.3.</note> and to all that were with him, <hi>Put away the ſtrange gods that are amongſt you, and be clean, and change your garments, and let us ariſe and go up to</hi> Bethel, <hi>and I will build there an altar unto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bethel.</note> 
               <hi>who was with me in the day of my distreſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 35.3.</note> 
               <hi>and was mith me in the way that I went.</hi> Altars or Churches may have many Benefactors, but <hi>Jacob</hi> will be the ſole Founder of his Altar, built at <hi>Bethel;</hi> yet ſee the bleſſed effects of a religious motion, one may build, but many may have the Bleſſing in this caſe. See the Patriarch's haſtineſs, and Gods glory, in this ſacred progreſs; it was no ſooner moved, that Gods Altar ſhould be built, but preſently <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Houſhold, and all that were with him,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.4.</note> gave unto <hi>Jacob</hi> all the ſtrange gods that were in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33310:16"/>their hands, and all the ear-rings that were in their eares, to manifeſt their bounty and delight towards the Beauty of Holineſs; and, if the Patriarch will build an altar at <hi>Bethel,</hi> his Houſhold reſolve with their gold and ſilver, with their moſt precious jewels, to adorn and beautifie that holy ſtructure. Thus <hi>Jacob</hi>'s altar, and <hi>Moſe</hi>'s Tabernacle, and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, went up, and were made and beautified with ſeveral Offerings.<note place="margin">Exod. 25.2.</note> Thus without murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or repining, preſentment or complaint,<note place="margin">Exod. 35.5.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Neighbours, or <hi>Iſrael</hi> and his Houſhold, built and beautified the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar at <hi>Bethel.</hi> It is obſervable alſo, how the people proceeded with the Patriarch;<note place="margin">Gen. 35.3.4.</note> for he perſwadeth, and they obey: he ſaith, <hi>Let us ariſe, and go to</hi> Bethel, <hi>and I will make there an Altar unto God, who anſwered me in the day of my diſtreſs, and was with me in the way which I went.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inaures quae erant in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus eorum dicatas ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet alicui fictitio nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini <hi>Hu Grot.</hi> in loc.</note> And they gave unto <hi>Jacob</hi> all the ſtrange Gods in their hands, and the ear-rings which were in their eares, and the diſpoſing of theſe Gods, and jewels, gold and ſilver.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33310:17"/>which is obſervable of equal conſequence.<note place="margin">Gen. 35.4.</note> 
               <hi>And</hi> Jacob <hi>hid them under the Oak, which was by</hi> Sichem. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Oak;</hi> God, when he pleaſeth, can order, that fooliſh things ſhall confound the wiſe; and weak things ſhall confound the mighty;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.28.</note> and things which are not, ſhall bring to nought things that are. Thus God can prepare a Cave at <hi>Adullam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.1.</note> to ſecure his ſervant <hi>David</hi> from the fury of <hi>Saul;</hi> A cleft in the rock for his Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> to preſerve him from the rage and wrath of <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings 19.14.</note> and and curſed <hi>Jezabel.</hi> God can provide an Ark of wood for righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> and a fiſh for his ſervant <hi>Jonah,</hi> to preſerve them from the dangers of the deep,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.1.</note> and ſwelling of the waves.<note place="margin">Jonah. 1.17.</note> And thus God can (when he pleaſeth) make a Tree in the Woods, a <hi>Royal Dak,</hi> a Court, a Caſtle to defend Soveraignty from death, diſgrace, or danger, when Navies have revolted, and Armies have been routed, and the arms of fleſh have failed and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Thus <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhewed both his reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reaſon, when he erected his altar
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33310:17"/>at <hi>Bethel;</hi> It is likewiſe of high concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we take notice of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs Devotion or Dedication as well as of the Erection and Building of his Altar, which he calleth, <hi>El-Bethel,</hi> that is, <hi>the God of Bethel;</hi> or rather, <hi>the God of Gods houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.19.</note> God did here appear to <hi>Jacob</hi> in his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and therefore <hi>Jacob</hi> will here more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably appear before God in his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Dedication; and not onely build an Altar, but likewiſe give it a name and title of honour and diſtinction, to Gods glory; he calleth it <hi>El-Bethel,</hi> the <hi>God of Bethel:</hi> In theſe early and primitive times the Patriarch would have the God of Heaven to have an houſe on Earth, at leaſt an Altar for his ſacred worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. God is the <hi>God of order,</hi> and not the <hi>Authour of Confuſion:</hi> and while Pride and Carnal humours endeavour to build Towers towards Heaven; which prove a <hi>Babel:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.9.</note> the pious Patriarch will teach the World a leſſon of more humble and clear Devotion, and builds an Altar, and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates it to his Maker and Preſerver, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33310:18"/>calls it <hi>El-Bethel,</hi> the <hi>God of Gods houſe.</hi> It was the ſad complaint of <hi>Elijah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 910</note> againſt the Sacrilegious Murderers of that Age:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>That they had thrown down Gods Altars, and ſlain the Prophets with the ſword;</hi> but the Patriarch, in the Text gives the world a better example, he builds an Altar at <hi>Bethel,</hi> and devotes it to Almighty God; and at <hi>Shalem</hi> where he pitched his Tent, he erected there an Altar,<note place="margin">Gen. 33.18.20.</note> and called it <hi>El-Elohe-Iſrael,</hi> That is, <hi>God the God of Iſrael;</hi> that is, <hi>Jacobs God.</hi> Now as God is well pleaſed with holy and humble De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion;<note place="margin">Moneantur interim mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeri, ut ſi ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperare nolint prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, ſaltem Sacrilegis ſua non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant ne majori ſe ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. D. Aug. Epiſt. <hi>53.</hi> Iſay <hi>5.6.7. Jere: 7.11. Mat: 21 14. Mark: 11.17 Luk: 19 46.</hi>
               </note> ſo is he diſpleaſe with no ſins more than Sacriledg, or rude Prophaneſs, which is <hi>calcitratio,</hi> a kind of <hi>kicking at Gods honour,</hi> and a Robbing of his glory, Chriſt could not endure it at his Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, taunting the Prophaners in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with a ſharp truth, and ſaying, <hi>It is written my houſe ſhall be called the houſe of Prayer, but ye have made it a Den of Thieves.</hi> Thus the Patriarch, as he devoutly builds an Altar, he will have it bear Gods name, <hi>El-Bethel.</hi> I have now done with the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33310:18"/>Dedication of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Altars, and in the cloſe come to the occaſion or cauſe why he built an Altar; why at <hi>Bethel;</hi> and why called <hi>Gods houſe, Moſes</hi> hath ſummed up in brief the Patriarchs duty, as well as his devotion; <hi>Becauſe God there appeared to him, when he fled from the face of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Eſau. In which words ſee couched,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.7.</note> Firſt, his danger; Secondly, his deliverance; Thirdly, his duty or thankfulneſs: <hi>danger</hi> in <hi>Eſau</hi> purſuing his Brother <hi>Jacob; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> from God; who appeared when <hi>Jacob</hi> fled; <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> in <hi>Jacob,</hi> who reſcued from <hi>Eſau</hi>'s fury, builds an Altar as a pledg of Piety and Thankfulneſs. Thus <hi>Noah</hi> delivered from being drowned, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up odour and ſweet incenſe to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.31:</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> redeemed from Captivity in <hi>Egypt,</hi> did obſerve the Paſso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and did compoſe his Song of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving;<note place="margin">Exod. 15.1.2.</note> Thus <hi>Iſrael,</hi> delivered from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malech,</hi> built an altar,<note place="margin">Exo. 17.15.</note> and called it <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah Niſſi,</hi> that is, <hi>the Lord my Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> or, <hi>Enſign.</hi> It was King <hi>David</hi>'s deliverance from dangers, and his advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33310:19"/>to a Throne,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 22.1. Pſal. 18.1.</note> that occaſioned his Song of Thankſgiving, when the Lord had delivered him out of the hands of <hi>Saul,</hi> and of all his Enemies. It was this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Thankfulneſs, that made this Royal Prophet to prepare Materials to build Gods Temple, and made him the Pen of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Writer, to compoſe the Book of Pſalms,<note n="(*)" place="margin">Sicut Manna habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum &amp; omnem ſapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſuavita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; ſie Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Pſalmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omne ſpirituale do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumentum. <hi>Ludol. in Proaemio Pſalmorum.</hi> Cùm in choro canitur, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Eccleſiae Deum lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant is; cùm à juſt is, verba Deum Iau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantis; cùm à peccatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, verba veniam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precantis, <hi>Idem Ludo.</hi>
               </note> which, when they are ſung in the Quire, are the Voice of the Church honouring God; when by any righteous perſon, are the words of one praiſing God; and if a ſinner chaunt the holy Hymns, they are the voice of a poor Penitent, craving mercy and pardon for their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. From theſe pious Examples of the Patriarchs and Prophets, many bleſſed Chriſtians have taken great encouragement to be Founders and Benefactors to the Chriſtian Churches. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> was a Primitive and early Patron for the founding, endowing, and building, of Churches for the<note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius. Cambden.</hi> Brit. pa. 270.</note> Chriſtian Religion. But if we look nearer home, we may find how God hath inclin'd the hearts of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33310:19"/>Princes, pious Prelates, and other good Chriſtians, to build Churches, to found Schools and Colledges, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Chriſtian Faith, and advancement of Learning. Our own An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and Hiſtories tell us, That <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus,</hi> King of the Eaſt <hi>Saxons,</hi> firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> being then <hi>Delubrum Apollinis,</hi> to be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Temple, and dedicated to the honour, name, and memory, of the Apoſtle St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and that of <hi>Diana</hi>'s, to St. <hi>Paul.</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> improved this Act of Chriſtian Pietty, and made choice of that Church<note n="(*)" place="margin">Eduar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Rex, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnomento Confeſior, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi in ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruxit, &amp; ex decimis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegro, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimoniis to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ Angliâ diſperſis, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit. <hi>Guil. Camden. Brit. p. 270.</hi>
               </note> for the Royal Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of himſelf and Succeſſors, endowing it yearly with the Tenths of all his Royal Revenues, and with ample Patrimonies in many Parts of <hi>England.</hi> This Church and Fabrick was inlarged<note n="(*)" place="margin">Hanc Eduardi fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, novam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Eccleſiam ſpeciosâ ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturâ exaedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficavit. <hi>Cam. Brit. p. 271.</hi>
               </note> and beautified by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third; and theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples were ſo effectual, that the Word of God grew and multiplied<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 12.24.</note> exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. Cathedralls, and Churches, and Chappels, were built, endowed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33310:20"/>not on the Doctrine and blind Deluſions of Popiſh <hi>Merits,</hi> but out of pure <hi>Devotion</hi> to Gods Honour; and out of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> for great Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of imminent dangers. Thus our own Hiſtories tell us of that immortal Prince,<note place="margin">Cùm Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam ſuis victoriis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſus eſſet. <hi>Camd. Brit. pag. 271.</hi>
               </note> King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, (*) That he founded a Royal Chappel near <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and dedicated it to the name and honour of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> in a devout and humble thankfulneſs for ſo many Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, and his liberation from ſo many dangers, when he had Wars with <hi>France.</hi> This Noble Monarch having at the ſame time <hi>John</hi> the French King, and <hi>David</hi> the Scotch King his Priſoners at <hi>Windſor,</hi> in honour and thankfulneſs to Almighty God, built the Chappel at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and devoted that ſacred Structure to the Honour of Sr. <hi>George,</hi> and the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> for the better encouragement of Chriſtian Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and truly Heroick Valour:<note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t virtutem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus, praemiis, &amp; ſplendore, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coraret. <hi>Idem pag. 198.</hi>
               </note> And as King <hi>David</hi> prepared rich Materials, and King <hi>Solomon</hi> built and finiſhed the ſtately Temple at <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> So King <hi>Edward</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33310:20"/>the Third firſt built the Royal Chappel; and King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth beautified and adorned that Princely Piece. In the like Devotion, King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Kings Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and his Royal Conſort <hi>Queens Colledge. Henry the Seventh</hi> after his Victory at <hi>Boſworth</hi>-field, marched up to <hi>London,</hi> and with the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers Colours taken in the Battle, and devoted them in St. <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church, in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God for his and the Kingdoms deliverance from <hi>Richard the Thirds</hi> Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; and his ſucceſs, did not puff up his Princely Soul, but, encreaſed his Devotion, which occaſioned him to build his Royal Chappel at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> dedicated to the name and memory of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which <hi>Leland</hi> calls <hi>Miraculum Mundi</hi> the wonder of the World. <hi>Henry the Eighth,</hi> manger the malice of Popiſh mouths, founded and ſettled the four Biſhopricks of <hi>Oxford, Cheſter, Gloceſter,</hi> and <hi>Peterborough;</hi> and <hi>Trinity Golledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> record the bounty
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33310:21"/>of that famous Prince and Patron of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>King Edward the Sixth</hi> and <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> were noble founders of Schools and Hoſpitals. <hi>King James</hi> was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorer of the Biſhopricks in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the preſerver of them in <hi>England,</hi> and a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor to many in <hi>Ireland. King Charles the Firſt</hi> was not onely a <hi>Patron</hi> in his proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, but in his blacker dayes a <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> and in the end a <hi>Martyr,</hi> for his Crown, the Church, and the Lawes. His Majeſty when he was reſtored to his Crown, God did aſſiſt him to reſtore the Biſhops to their Sees, and the Churchmen to their Cures in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and it was his piety and Royal bounty to deſign Augmentations to poor Biſhopricks, Impropriations and Glebe-lands to poor Vicaridges, and a <hi>Kings Colledge</hi> to the Citty of <hi>Dublin,</hi> for the better Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Learning and Religion. But his Majeſties Royal deſign was diſappointed by an unhappy event. And now sa Pious Princes have been Gracious and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33310:21"/>kind to Gods Church; So Religious and holy Biſhops have been happy examples in their works of Piety, witneſs the firſt Colledge in <hi>Cambridge</hi> founded and built by <hi>Hugo Balſam</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to St. <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Primum Collegium Sancti pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri Domus vocatur, quòd Hugo Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Elienſis extruxit, Anno <hi>1280.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Merton Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> one of the moſt Ancient of all in that Univerſity, founded by <hi>Gualter Merton</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> And, as Princes and Praelates, ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers moſt noble and godly worthies have been Patrons, founders, and Benefactors, to Learning and Gods Church; others as Pious Chriſtian Heroes, have in their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity been <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> in their adverſity have been <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> and at their death <hi>Martyrs</hi> to aſſert and vindicate their zeal and love to Gods Church, the Kings Crown, and the Kingdoms Lawes. I have thus opened the Text, and ſhewed <hi>Jacobs</hi> danger, his deliverance and his duty, or Thankfulneſs; Remember that thoſe who brought Purple, blew, or lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, for the Tabernacle were accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33310:22"/>The widows mite was entertained, and good meaning towards Gods Church. <hi>Now to God the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be all Honour and Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen, Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33310:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
